<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>rswilson32.github.io</title>
    <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io" />
    <updated>2024-03-26T09:13:26-07:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Roger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://rswilson32.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Live Metro Bike Availability Map</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/live-metro-bike-availability-map/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/live-metro-bike-availability-map/</id>

        <updated>2024-03-26T09:13:26-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Here's a fun map: Thanks!
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Here's a fun map:</p>
<div style="max-width: 1000px; max-height: 600px;"><div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="1000" height="600" style="width: 1000px; height: 600px;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/13/bikemap.html">&lt;\iframe&gt; scrolling="no"&gt;</iframe></div></div>
<p>Thanks!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>ASL Alphabet Recognition Model</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/asl-alphabet-recognition-model/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/asl-alphabet-recognition-model/</id>

        <updated>2023-12-28T17:01:48-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/american_sign_language-2.PNG" alt="" />
                    The Project This model classifies images of the American Sign Language (ASL) alphabet. According to the National Institute of Health, over 860,000 North Americans use ASL either as a primary or secondary language as of 2006, and we hope that our model can contribute to making communication more accessible for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/american_sign_language-2.PNG" alt="" />
                <div class="container-lg px-3 my-5 markdown-body">
<h3 id="the-project">The Project<a class="anchorjs-link " href="https://rswilson32.github.io/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model/#the-project" aria-label="Anchor" data-anchorjs-icon=""></a></h3>
<p>This model classifies images of the American Sign Language (ASL) alphabet. According to the National Institute of Health, over 860,000 North Americans use ASL either as a primary or secondary language as of 2006, and we hope that our model can contribute to making communication more accessible for individuals who sign. This was my final project for my machine learning class at UCLA. While it was a group project, we worked on creating three separate convolutional neural networks (CNN) to compare different architectures and their performances on our data. The following code and opencv program were my contributions. Since we were developing an image recognition model, convolutional neural networks were the natural choice as they are flexible, and we need a model that is invariant under translation of the input. We believe that using convolutional neural networks will maximize our overall image recognition accuracy.</p>
<h3 id="the-data">Data<a class="anchorjs-link " href="https://rswilson32.github.io/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model/#the-data" aria-label="Anchor" data-anchorjs-icon=""></a></h3>
<p>The training and testing data is from the Sign Language MNIST data, which contains 27,455 training images and 7,712 testing images. Each training and test case represents a label (0-25) as a one-to-one map for each alphabetic letter A-Z (and no cases for 9=J or 25=Z because they involve motions). Each 28x28 pixel image is represented as a vector with grayscale values between 0-255. The original hand gesture image data represented multiple users repeating the gesture against different backgrounds. To create new data, “an image pipeline was used based on ImageMagick and included cropping to hands-only, gray-scaling, resizing, and then creating at least 50+ variations to enlarge the quantity”.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/american_sign_language.PNG" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/american_sign_language-xs.PNG 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/american_sign_language-sm.PNG 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/american_sign_language-md.PNG 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/american_sign_language-lg.PNG 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/american_sign_language-xl.PNG 1600w"  alt="" width="876" height="489"></figure>
<h3 id="model">Model<a class="anchorjs-link " href="https://rswilson32.github.io/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model/#model" aria-label="Anchor" data-anchorjs-icon=""></a></h3>
<p>The model is built in PyTorch with four convolution layers and a fully connected layer at the end. I also employed max pooling to down-sample our feature maps. At the end of our pipeline, the network includes two fully connected layers followed by batch normalization and dropout. I used dropout in the fully connected layer instead of in the convolutions. The first convolutional layer processes a single input channel, gradually increasing the number of channels in the next layers. ReLU activation functions are applied throughout the network. A dropout rate of 0.2 is also applied at the end. Through hyperparameter tuning, this CNN achieved 98.2% accuracy with a batch size of 64, Adam optimizer, a learning rate of 0.001, and 8 epochs.</p>
<h3 id="camera-application">Camera Application<a class="anchorjs-link " href="https://rswilson32.github.io/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model/#camera-application" aria-label="Anchor" data-anchorjs-icon=""></a></h3>
<p>We also implemented a real-time ASL alphabet camera recognition system using the opencv library designed for computer vision and my trained model’s weights. The program recognizes images in a given region of interest (ROI) which we designate with a green square. The frame is then captured, set to gray-scale, and blurred. We are then able to classify the hand gesture using our previously trained CNN.</p>
<h3>Code</h3>
<p>The code can be found on <a href="https://github.com/rswilson32/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this GitHub repository</a>. To run the camera application, download <a href="https://github.com/rswilson32/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model/blob/main/camera_recognition.py" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">camera_application.py</a>, which has the CNN, classifying function and camera function, and <a href="https://github.com/rswilson32/ASL-MNIST-recognition-model/blob/main/cnn156.pt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">cnn156.pt</a>, the PyTorch parameters for the CNN. simply running 'python camera_application.py' in your console will start the camera.</p>
</div>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/aslmath.PNG" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/aslmath-xs.PNG 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/aslmath-sm.PNG 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/aslmath-md.PNG 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/aslmath-lg.PNG 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/12/responsive/aslmath-xl.PNG 1600w"  alt="" width="843" height="246"></figure>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>LA Tree Coverage Analysis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/la-tree-coverage-analysis/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/la-tree-coverage-analysis/</id>

        <updated>2023-12-13T00:17:07-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/11/skyline-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    ----&gt; click here &lt;----
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/11/skyline-2.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><a href="https://arcg.is/1f9XTz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">----&gt; click here &lt;----</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Metro Bikeshare Data</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/metro/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/metro/</id>

        <updated>2024-03-14T22:13:32-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/mbs-4.png" alt="" />
                    I've always loved biking, so I was ecstatic to get a free annual Metro Bikeshare pass this last spring. For an explanation of the system, here's an exerpt is from the metro bikeshare website: The Metro Bike Share system makes bikes available 24/7, 365 days a year in Downtown LA,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/mbs-4.png" alt="" />
                <p>I've always loved biking, so I was ecstatic to get a free annual Metro Bikeshare pass this last spring. For an explanation of the system, here's an exerpt is from the <a href="https://bikeshare.metro.net/about/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">metro bikeshare website:</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Metro Bike Share system makes bikes available 24/7, 365 days a year in Downtown LA, Central LA, Hollywood, North Hollywood and on the Westside. Metro Bike Share offers convenient round-the-clock access to a fleet of bicycles for short trips. Metro Bike Share is one of LA Metro's multiple public transportation options for Angelenos and visitors to get around.<br><br>Metro Bike Share is a fast, easy, and fun way to ride, anytime. Get a bike from any Metro Bike Share station, go for a ride, and properly return it. It’s easy — just like riding a bike!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Since getting my membership, I've been able to bike to my classes, the grocery store, the gym, and more. It's faster than walking, I avoid traffic, and it's overall just fun! I've rarely had issues of crowded stations or empty stations at UCLA, and even if I did, there were always some nearby in Westwood.</p>
<div class="flex flex-grow flex-col max-w-full gap-3 gizmo:gap-0">
<div class="min-h-[20px] text-message peer flex flex-col items-start gap-3 whitespace-pre-wrap break-words peer-[.text-message]:mt-5 overflow-x-auto" data-message-author-role="assistant" data-message-id="b1b5ef19-b5cf-4039-bb68-d70d73ffbc7f">
<div class="markdown prose w-full break-words dark:prose-invert light">
<p>However, during a recent visit to Santa Monica beach, my friend and I had a pretty tough time trying to use the Metro Bikeshare system. The bike stations were all full, and we had to walk more than half a mile to find an available bike. At the Metro E line station, there were even more people waiting to return their bikes than those trying to rent one.</p>
<p>Inspired by this experience, I decided to dive into a college project to look into how popular Metro Bikeshare stations and routes are across Los Angeles. I used <a href="https://bikeshare.metro.net/about/data/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">public data</a> from the city to analyze Metro Bikeshare's demand over the two years.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="600" style="border: 1; display: block; margin: auto;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/bike_cal.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<div style="float: right; width: 60%;"><div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="620" height="620" style="border: 1; display: block; margin: auto;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/station_popularity.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div></div>
<p>It's immediately evident that Metro Bikeshare has experienced a surge in popularity over the past year. In 2021, the daily average rentals stood at around xx bikes, with a notable exception in September, where the numbers spiked to over 900 per day (maybe a promotional event?). However, since then, there has been a consistent increase, with an average of xxx bike rentals per day. An important factor to consider in this context is the continuous expansion of Metro Bikeshare stations. Notably, stations in Burbank were only introduced in January 2021, and the UCLA stations (which I use) were not available until January 2023. Even when I normalized each station by popularity, it's apparent how much more popular Metro Bikeshare has become recently. This leads us to the original question: In which regions does bikeshare demand outweigh others, and how should Metro Bikeshare respond to this evolving demand?</p>
<p> </p>
<div style="float: right; width: 60%;"><div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="620" height="620" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_map.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div></div>
<p style="margin: 0;">I have decided to normalize the number of bike rentals per station. And, for clarity, I've graphed the k/2 most popular routes among the k stations in the dataset. Hovering over a station (dot) in these visualizations includes the station number, name, and its average daily rental count. I'll put my code on my GitHub.</p>
<p style="margin: 0;">It's evident from this visual that the most frequented routes are concentrated along Santa Monica's shorefront, UCLA's campus, Culver City, USC's campus, and the downtown area of Los Angeles. Metro Bikeshare also categorizes these stations into three distinct regions: Santa Monica (region 2), Downtown Los Angeles (region 9), and North Hollywood + Burbank (region 1). We'll analyze these regions more closely below.</p>
<p> </p>
<select id="plotDropdown1">
<option value="freq_2">Region 2</option>
<option value="freq_19">Region 1, 9</option>
</select>
<div id="plotContainer1" style="float: right; width: 60%;"></div>
<p style="margin: 0;">(Note: To access maps, please click around on the dropdown menus, I have no idea how to fix this.) When we narrow our focus to Region 2, the most frequented routes converge on the Downtown Santa Monica E Line station (station 4215) and Ocean Front Walk &amp; Navy (station 4214), with both averaging 60 rentals per day. Given Santa Monica's status as a tourist hotspot, it's probable that most of these rentals are from visitors instead of commuters. Take for example station Dockweiler Beach (station 4544), while being at the southernmost point of the beach, still averages over 14 rentals a day. It's interesting to note that even though UCLA's stations were built relatively later (with some only 7 months ago), they're featured prominently in the dataset. It would be very beneficial to expand the station network in Westwood, particularly for students who may bike to class (like me!).</p>
<p style="margin: 0;">When we focus on regions 1 and 9, we observe a complex web of routes throughout downtown, with 7th &amp; Flower (station 3005) standing out as the most popular, averaging 38 rentals per day. USC's also a popular hub, especially with its stations' vicinity to DTLA. Interestingly, North Hollywood isn't that popular. While it's true that these stations are relatively new, I thought that the fact that it's a touristy location would offset that.</p>
<p> </p>
<p style="margin: 0;"><select id="plotDropdown2">
<option value="freq_walk">Walk-Up</option>
<option value="freq_day">Daily Pass</option>
<option value="freq_month">Monthly Pass</option>
<option value="freq_annual">Annual Pass</option>
</select></p>
<div id="plotContainer2" style="float: left; width: 60%;"></div>
<p>
<script>
		const plotDropdown1 = document.getElementById("plotDropdown1");
		const plotContainer1 = document.getElementById("plotContainer1");

		const plotDropdown2 = document.getElementById("plotDropdown2");
		const plotContainer2 = document.getElementById("plotContainer2");

		function updateIframe(selectedPlot, plotContainer) {
			plotContainer.innerHTML = ""; // Clear the container

			if (selectedPlot) {
				const iframe = document.createElement("iframe");
				iframe.width = "620";
				iframe.height = "620";
				iframe.scrolling = "no";
				iframe.frameBorder = "0";
				iframe.src = `https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/${selectedPlot}.html`;
				plotContainer.appendChild(iframe);
			}
		}

		plotDropdown1.addEventListener("change", function() {
			updateIframe(plotDropdown1.value, plotContainer1);
		});

		plotDropdown2.addEventListener("change", function() {
			updateIframe(plotDropdown2.value, plotContainer2);
		});
	</script>
</p>
<p style="margin: 0;">When looking at the data by filtering for rental types, we get more cool results. Metro Bikeshare users have two primary options for renting a bike: they can either make an on-the-spot rental (walk-up) or use their TAP account with a membership (daily, monthly, or annual). Focusing on walk-up and daily pass rentals reveals a striking concentration in Santa Monica, particularly at stations 4214 and 4215, where nearly 75% of the daily rentals from these stations come from walk-up and day pass users. Given Santa Monica's touristy status, I think its safe to label these renters as visitors wanting to explore the Pier, beach, promenade, and more. And if these visitors are unable to find available stations along the beach, they seem to drop off their bikes a few blocks inland.</p>
<p style="margin: 0;">On the other hand, monthly and annual pass rentals are predominantly centered in downtown Los Angeles, USC, UCLA, and Culver City, suggesting a focus on commuting needs. However, it's worth noting that even the most popular station for annual pass rentals, Figueroa &amp; 8th (station 3035), averages only around 4 rentals per day from annual pass holders. To look further into this, the following graph illustrates that a majority of bike rentals are from monthly pass holders who are responsible for most of the increased rentals over the past two years. It's reasonable to speculate that tourists typically opt for daily or walk-up rentals, and many new riders may be hesitant to commit to an annual pass upfront.</p>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="300" style="border: 1; display: block; margin: auto;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/stacked.html">
		&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<p>So far, all of my analysis has been on Metro Bikeshare's public, downloadable data. Which is great! But something I really wanted to look into was Metro's API, which gives realtime information on the number of bikes at each station.</p>
<p>With this API, along with various station attributes, such as working status and total bike capacity, I was able to map the average capacity of each station over the past 2.5 years.<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" width="800" height="400" style="border: 1; display: block; margin: auto;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/bike_avg_capacity.html">
		&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<p>It's not surprising to hear that station 4215 near the E-Line in Santa Monica is consistently full (this is the station that I couldn't return my bike to and had to bike down towards Dockweiler to return it!). One interesting observation is that two nearby stations, 4214 and 4219, are often found to be nearly empty. My assumption is that visitors rent bikes at stations near attractions or where they parked, and are reluctant to walk a significant distance to return it. So station 4215, being closest to the pier, is consistently full, while those farther inland are not. In contrast, when we zoom into Downtown Los Angeles (DTLA), for example, we notice that most stations maintain an average of around 50% capacity. This is likely because DTLA stations are always within a few blocks of each other, so riders can easily find another station. This convenience is definitely preferred over areas like Venice and Santa Monica, where the stations are more dispersed, making it less practical for users to find an alternative nearby station.</p>
<p>With all of this in mind, here are some reccomendations for improving the Metro Bikeshare system:</p>
<ol>
<li>Given the heavy reliance on the E-Line bike station in Downtown Santa Monica, it would be beneficial to build more stations in this area. Potential areas include along Wilshire, Ocean Ave., and Broadway. Notably, Ocean Front Walk, due to its constant foot traffic, could be an ideal spot. Furthermore, given the consistent popularity of bike routes from Santa Monica to Dockweiler Beach, having more stations along the beach, especially farther north on PCH, would cater to the year-round demand.</li>
<li>Considering that nearly 75% of rides in Santa Monica are through walk-up rentals and day passes, increasing the availability of stations or increasing promotional efforts for Metro Bikeshare could be very beneficial. Conversely, in areas like downtown Los Angeles, USC, UCLA, and Culver City, where well-established stations predominantly are used by riders with monthly and annual passes, Metro Bikeshare should promote annual passes more for easier commuting.</li>
<li>Westwood, Sawtelle and West Hollywood would definitely benefit from new Metro bike stations, especially after seeing how popular UCLA's stations have become in seven months alone. It would also make my commute a lot easier :)</li>
</ol>
<p>This was a fun project to work on, and I'm more confident with Python and Plotly to create the visuals that I need. More importantly, I really enjoy using Metro Bikeshare, so discovering that their rental data and API are public was incredible. I encountered some of the difficulties with renting bikes at UCLA and Santa Monica firsthand, and the data helped me identify areas for improvement. It's also exciting to note how popular Metro Bikeshare has become in recent months, and I look forward to seeing how my visuals will evolve as I incorporate new quarterly data.</p>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" style="display: none;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_2.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" style="display: none;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_19.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" style="display: none;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_walk.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" style="display: none;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_day.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" style="display: none;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_month.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
<div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" style="display: none;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/10/freq_annual.html">&lt;\iframe&gt;</iframe></div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Bike Rental Model</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/california-commuting-patterns-2/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/california-commuting-patterns-2/</id>

        <updated>2023-08-24T12:35:45-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/9/biking.webp" alt="" />
                    This data set of interest is of Capital Bikeshare rentals in 2011 and 2012, sourced from the UCI Machine Learning Repository. From the site: “Bike-sharing systems represent a new generation of traditional bike rentals, where the entire process - from membership and rental to return - has become automatic. With these&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/9/biking.webp" alt="" />
                <p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">This data set of interest is of</span> <a href="https://capitalbikeshare.com/">Capital Bikeshare</a> <span dir="ltr" role="presentation">rentals in 2011 and 2012, sourced from the</span> <a href="https://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/bike+sharing+dataset">UCI Machine Learning Repository</a><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">. From the site:</span></p>
<p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">“Bike-sharing systems represent a new generation of traditional bike rentals, where the entire process - from </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">membership and rental to return - has become automatic. With these systems, users can easily rent a bike </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">from a particular location and return it to another.</span> <span dir="ltr" role="presentation">Currently, there are over 500 bike-sharing programs </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">worldwide, which comprise more than 500,000 bicycles.</span> <span dir="ltr" role="presentation">These systems are of great interest due to their </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">important role in addressing traffic, environmental, and health issues.</span></p>
<p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">In addition to the interesting real-world applications of bike-sharing systems, the characteristics of the data </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">generated by these systems make them attractive for research. Unlike other transport services such as buses </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">or subways, the duration of travel, departure, and arrival positions are explicitly recorded in these systems. </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">This feature turns bike-sharing systems into a virtual sensor network that can be used for sensing mobility </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">in the city.</span> <span dir="ltr" role="presentation">Therefore, it is expected that most of the important events in the city could be detected by </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">monitoring this data.”</span></p>
<p>I was able to get a free year of Metro bikes through UCLA, and while this data is of D.C. rentals, I thought that modeling rental trends would be interesting. With the final model:</p>
<p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">Perceived temperature has the greatest influence on number of bikes rented: when we ran our regression </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">subsets test, it was the very first variable chosen. A 1 degree (F) increase in the temperature correspond to </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">5,596 bikes rented!</span></p>
<p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">Number of rented bikes also depends a fair amount on the day of the week: the farther into the week, the </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">more predicted bikes rented. </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">The greatest negative influences on rental count are rain (weathersit3), high windspeed, high humidity, and </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">holidays. These all make sense. </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">In all, 79% of the variation in total rented bike counts can be attributed to these variables. We can see that </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">from our regressions subset test that a model with just the date, weather situation and temperature serves </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">well enough, but if we have access to all of these variables, we might as well use them.</span></p>
<p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">This project can prove helpful for cities that want to adopt a rental bike system and help plan accordingly </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">for total number of stations and bikes needed. The D.C. bike company could also vary prices based on these </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">variables to maximize profits or maximize number of bikes used for certain days or periods. </span></p>
<p><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">This model only predicts total number of bikes rented per day.</span> <span dir="ltr" role="presentation">Future analysis on hourly rental counts </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">or location-based rental information could be interesting. It would also be interesting to create models for </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">casual rentals and registered rentals. We assumed that there was no difference in rental preferences for the </span><span dir="ltr" role="presentation">sake of this project.</span></p>
<p>The complete report can be found <a href="https://github.com/rswilson32/bikeshare/blob/main/bikeshare.pdf">here!</a></p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Fowler Analysis</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/fowler-analysis/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/fowler-analysis/</id>

        <updated>2022-12-08T09:47:53-08:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/7/fowler-3.jpg" alt="" />
                <p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>DataFest 2022</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/datafest-2022/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/datafest-2022/</id>

        <updated>2023-12-28T22:12:51-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/6/datafest-2.png" alt="" />
                    My team and I (the Data Dudes) competed in the UCLA ASA Datafest, an annual statistics competition. We were given 40 hours to analyze Yale research PLAY2PREVENT data focused on behavioral patterns in children. We made it through 2 rounds of presentations and surpassed 70 other teams. Our team won&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/6/datafest-2.png" alt="" />
                <p>My team and I (the Data Dudes) competed in the <a href="http://datafest.stat.ucla.edu/about/about-asa-datafest/">UCLA ASA Datafest</a>, an annual statistics competition. We were given 40 hours to analyze Yale research PLAY2PREVENT data focused on behavioral patterns in children. We made it through 2 rounds of presentations and surpassed 70 other teams. Our team won for our analysis of varying attention and interest levels among children. This experience strenghened my statistical skills and my coding abilities with extensive amounts of data! </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>California Commuting Patterns</title>
        <author>
            <name>Roger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://rswilson32.github.io/california-commuting-patterns/"/>
        <id>https://rswilson32.github.io/california-commuting-patterns/</id>

        <updated>2023-11-08T13:31:00-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/traffic-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    This data set contains data on modes of transportation to work for Californian Residents aged 16 years and older. Data is from the U.S. Census Bureau, Decennial Census and American Community Survey. The data can be found at the California Health and Human Services Open Data Website. According to the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/traffic-2.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>This data set contains data on modes of transportation to work for Californian Residents aged 16 years and older. Data is from the U.S. Census Bureau, Decennial Census and American Community Survey. The data can be found at <a href="https://data.chhs.ca.gov/dataset/transportation-to-work-2000-2006-2010/resource/87fa0619-708a-4d92-ba5d-879df338b46e">the California Health and Human Services Open Data Website</a>.</p>
<p>According to the source, "Commute trips to work represent 19% of travel miles in the United States," with cars being by far the most used mode of transportation. While cars are convenient, they are one of the deadliest modes of transportation and release harmful emissions into the atmosphere. According to the <a href="https://ww2.arb.ca.gov/">California Air Resources Board</a>, vehicles and cars account for approximately one-third of all of California's CO2 emissions and air pollutants.</p>
<p>Besides driving, commuters can take public transportation, bike, walk, work from home, or even carpool. All of these methods help take cars off of our roads, which can significantly cut emissions and save money.</p>
<p>Note that my full report with more analysis is on my GitHub. Some key visualizations:</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="border-radius: 20px;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/ggp_CA-2.png" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/ggp_CA-2-xs.png 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/ggp_CA-2-sm.png 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/ggp_CA-2-md.png 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/ggp_CA-2-lg.png 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/ggp_CA-2-xl.png 1600w"  width="900" height="623"></figure>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="border-radius: 20px;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/gg_SoCal.png" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_SoCal-xs.png 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_SoCal-sm.png 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_SoCal-md.png 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_SoCal-lg.png 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_SoCal-xl.png 1600w"  width="900" height="630"></figure>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="border-radius: 20px;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/gg_Bay.png" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_Bay-xs.png 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_Bay-sm.png 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_Bay-md.png 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_Bay-lg.png 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_Bay-xl.png 1600w"  width="900" height="630"></figure>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="border-radius: 20px;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/gg_bar.png" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_bar-xs.png 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_bar-sm.png 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_bar-md.png 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_bar-lg.png 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_bar-xl.png 1600w"  width="900" height="630"></figure>
<figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img loading="lazy"  style="border-radius: 20px;" src="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/gg_line.png" sizes="(min-width: 37.5em) 1600px, 80vw" srcset="https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_line-xs.png 384w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_line-sm.png 600w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_line-md.png 768w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_line-lg.png 1200w ,https://rswilson32.github.io/media/posts/5/responsive/gg_line-xl.png 1600w"  width="900" height="630"></figure>
<p>A majority of commuters in Berkeley and San Francisco take public transportation or carpool to work, far above the state-wide averages. It’s also interesting that 19% of commuters in Davis bike to work, then the state average is only 1%.</p>
<p>Overall, the percent of Californians taking alternative modes of transportation to work had steadily decreased statewide, and 72.3% of Californians drive alone to work. It's important to note that all of the cities with the fastest transition interestingly all originally had a percentage lower than the state average.</p>
<p>This project was very interesting. I got a lot of practice working with dplyr, graphing locations, organizing data sets, and so much more.</p>
<p>It's important to note that the latest data in this data set is from the 2010 census. Our data also focuses only on commutes for Californians with paid work aged 16 and older. The data excludes driving for school, errands, vacations, and more.</p>
<p>Our analysis of the 200 most populated Californian cities helps shed some light on how car-dependent our state is. Many cities don't have a great public bus system. Others have so few sidewalks that walking or biking to work is just impossible. Still, cities have been improving accessibility to more environmentally friendly and economical modes of transportation.</p>
<p>This data set was accessed from <a href="https://data.chhs.ca.gov/dataset/transportation-to-work-2000-2006-2010/resource/87fa0619-708a-4d92-ba5d-879df338b46e">the California Health and Human Services Open Data Website</a>. They provided amazing data dictionaries, narrative examples, and research sources.</p>
<p><a href="https://eriqande.github.io/rep-res-web/lectures/making-maps-with-R.html">Eric C. Anderson's GitHub repository</a> on making maps in R was an incredible source. I used this reference for all of my ggplot maps.</p>
<p>I used this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_counties_in_California">Wikipedia article on Californian counties</a> for more great background information and its tables.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
